Finding Aid for William P. Lemon Papers 1908-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William P. Lemon papers 1908-1966
Lemon, William Philip, 1882-1967.
18 linear feet
Presbyterian clergyman, longtime pastor of the First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1934-1951; correspondence, copies of essays and book reviews written for religious periodicals, sermons and addresses, mimeographed study notes of talks given in Detroit before the Men's Club for the Study of Religion, religious and literary notebooks, and travel journals.
851727 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. William P. Lemon (donor no. 4681 ) and came to the library in different accessions, 1968, 1978, and 1995.
The collection is open for research.
William P. Lemon was a Presbyterian clergyman. He was pastor of Calvary Presbyterian Church, Newark, New Jersey, 1915-1921, of Andrew Church, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1921-1931, of the First Presbyterian Church of Iowa City, Iowa, 1931-1934, and the First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1934-1951.
The series in the collection are: Biographical; Correspondence; Writings; Speeches, sermons, lectures; Miscellaneous notes; Scriptures; Literary Studies; and Scrapbooks, journals, etc.
Subjects:
Andrew Church (Minneapolis, Minn.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Calvary Presbyterian Church (Newark, N.J.); Clergy--United States.; Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Iowa City, Iowa); Iowa City (Iowa); Lemon, William Philip, 1882-1967.; Men's Club for the Study of Religion (Detroit, Mich.); Minneapolis (Minn.); Newark (N.J.); Presbyterian Church.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Travelers.; Voyages and travels.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Andrews Presbyterian Church (Minneapolis, Minn.); Christmas.; Clergymen.; Costumes.; Easter.; Lemon, William Philip, 1882-1967.; Pageants.; Tableaux.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Sermons.
- Biographical
  - Biographical and personal material (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Ann Arbor First Presbyterian Church (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated and fragmentary (Box 1)
  - 1913-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1966 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Student papers of W.P. Lemon (Box 1)
  - Published writings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to Editor of Christian Century written under the pseudonym of Quintus Quiz, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Editor of Christian Century written under the pseudonym of Quintus Quiz, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Quintus Quiz drafts and related correspondence (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of articles written for Monday Morning (Box 1)
  - Poetry (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of book reviews, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of book reviews written for Monday Morning and The Presbyterian Tribune (Box 1)
  - Book reviews
    - Miscellaneous periodicals (Box 1)
    - The Presbyterian Tribune, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Christian Century, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of essays (Box 2)
    - "Religion in Account with Life" (Box 2)
    - "The Preacher as a Man of Letters" (Box 2)
    - "How to Know the Bible" (Box 2)
    - "The Letter that Moved the World", 2 volumes (Box 2)
      Lectures on Paul's letter to the Romans
    - "The Letter that Moved the World" (Background and miscellaneous material) (Box 2)
    - "Religion in Account with Economics" (Box 2)
    - "Religion and Science Down to Date" (Box 2)
- Speeches sermons, lectures
  - Notices of speeches and program of Lemon appearances (Box 2)
  - Printed sermons (Box 2)
  - News clippings of sermons and speeches (Box 2)
  - Sermons and addresses on education, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches and articles largely concerning Presbyterianism (Box 2)
  - Sermons and sermon notes largely concerning communion, Thanksgiving, food, blood, etc., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Year-end sermons summarizing the meaning of the preceding year
    (including review of the events of the year)
    - 1918-1922 (Box 2)
    - 1923 (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 2)
    - 1928-1930 (Box 2)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 2)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1947 (Box 2)
  - Sermons largely relating to Memorial Day, Armistice Day, and the Unknown Soldier (Box 2)
  - Christmas sermons and addresses, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Sermons and addresses (General), 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Sermons and sermon notes, 16 folders (Box 3)
  - Lectures on Biblical Literature given at the University of Minnesota 1923, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Men's Club for the Study of Religion
    - Miscellanea (Box 4)
    - Letters of appreciation 1941, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes (General), 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes (comparative religions) (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes (Jesus) (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes (God) (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes ("What is Christianity?") (Box 4)
  - Booklet containing mimeographed lecture notes on the Bible entitled, "Toward the Understanding of the Bible" (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed lecture notes on the Bible, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 13)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 14)
    (continued)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 15)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 16)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 17)
  - Notebooks containing sermons (Box 18)
  - Church plays and pageants (Box 4)
    - "God's Foreigner" (Box 4)
    - "Risen In-Deed" (Box 4)
    - "East and West; a pageant of Pilgrims" (Box 4)
    - "Bread of Life" (Thanksgiving pageant) (Box 4)
    - "Out of Dead Hopes" (Thanksgiving pageant) (Box 4)
    - "Bible of the World" (Box 4)
    - Christmas pageants (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous notes
  arranged topically
  - Old Testament, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Song of Solomon (Box 4)
  - Isaiah (Box 4)
  - Jeremiah (Box 4)
  - Genesis (Box 4)
  - Exodus and Leviticus (Box 4)
  - Numbers and Deuteronomy (Box 4)
  - Joshua, Judges, and Ruth (Box 4)
  - First and Second Samuel (Box 4)
  - First and Second Kings (Box 4)
  - Chronicles, Ezra, and Nehemiah (Box 4)
  - Esther (Box 4)
  - Psalms, Proverbs, Ecclesiastes (Box 4)
  - Lamentations (Box 4)
  - New Testament, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Israel and the Bible, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Religions of the World, 9 folders (Box 5)
  - Existentialism (Box 5)
  - Egypt (Box 5)
- Scriptures
  (arranged by topic)
  - Advent and Christmas (Box 5)
  - Major Prophets (Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel) (Box 5)
  - Minor Prophets (Box 5)
  - Great Scriptural Passages (Box 5)
  - Life of Christ (Box 5)
  - Life of Peter (Box 5)
  - Scriptures for the Church Year (Box 5)
  - Special Scripture Readings (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (Box 5)
- Literary studies
  (mimeographed notes, sermons and essays, etc.)
  - Drama (Box 6)
  - Greek classics (Box 6)
  - J.M. Barrie and G.B. Shaw (Box 6)
  - T.S. Eliot and John Masefield (Box 6)
  - John Milton (Box 6)
  - Thomas Carlyle (Box 6)
  - Alfred Tennyson (Box 6)
  - Arthurian Legend (Box 6)
  - Robert Browning, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Dostoievsky (Box 6)
  - Charles Dickens (Box 6)
  - Frederick Goethe (Box 6)
  - Dante (Box 6)
  - William Shakespeare (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous literary essays (Box 6)
  - Essay series: "Literature in account with (Box 6)
  - Essay series: "Literature and the Christian Religion" (Box 6)
  - Mimeographed literary notes (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks, journals, etc.
  - Personal scrapbook kept while in Wales, South Dakota, and Newark, New Jersey 1902-1915 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook containing correspondence, clippings photographs, and biographical miscellanea, 1877-1978 (Box 7)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Notebook containing brief diary entries, clippings, photographs, and biographical miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Travel journals
    - Europe 1908 (Box 7)
    - Alaska 1934 (Box 7)
    - Europe 1936 (Box 7)
  - Report of the Conference of the Association of Presbyterian University Pastors at Westminster Lodge, Saugatuck, Michigan June 23-27, 1941 (Box 7)
    (include study notes prepared by W.P. Lemon)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Notebooks containing study and research materials on the Bible (Box 7)
  - Notebooks containing study and research materials on the Bible (Box 8)
  - Notebooks containing study and research materials on the Bible (Box 9)
  - Notebooks containing study and research materials on the Bible (Box 10)
  - Journals containing clippings on important events of the day (Box 11)
  - Wall calendars containing notations on his daily activities (Box 12)